Never forget why you are the church.
Go ahead and turn your back.
Well, actually, we're going to be kind of everywhere this morning.
So what we're going to do is, you're just going to kind of keep up.
You can turn to Matthew 16 right now.
Um, This morning, we're taking a brief
break from our Romans series in Roman study.
And we're going to do a what could be
called, if you compare it to other series in
this church, a miniseries.
We're going to try to go 7 weeks.
I don't think that's going to include harvest day.
So technically, starting this week, it'll be 8
weeks, right, because harvest day, we won't go over this.
But, um, already
today, you have heard 2 important parts of
this local church.
You've heard our vision.
I heard Robin declaring that this morning.
Cedar Grow Baptist Church exists to create a
space where people and families can meet Jesus, find community,
and grow in their faith.
That is what we want to be.
That is the goal that we are trying to attain.
We want to be a place that people can come and
meet Jesus, find community and grow in their faith.
Listen, we live in a society, where there's a lot of fake Jesuses out there.
We live in a society where there's a lot of isolation out there.
We live in a society where families are no longer close.
There is no neighborly love anymore.
There's just, it's my family, it's my life.
It's my way, and we wonder why anxiety, and
depression, and discouragement, and stress, and just
the temptation to quit is all over our culture and
society because we're not living life together like we should.
At this church, we want it to be a community, a family
of believers, living life together.
And what we're gonna do, if we do that, we're gonna we're gonna naturally
grow in our faith.
And so that is our vision.
That is what we are looking and working to be.
And the beauty of this vision is that we are seeing it happen in real time.
This is exactly what we are seeing.
People that are coming in and saying, man, I've never been closer to God than when I've been here.
I've never, I've never had more friends that were believers than when
I started coming here.
Guys, that is not something that should be taken for granted.
That is a big deal.
And so this is our vision.
But we're going to accomplish the vision through our mission actions, and you heard that too.
What is our mission here at Cedar Grove Baptist Church?
Our purpose is to love others unconditionally, learn about
God increasingly, live to share Jesus, intentionally,
and lead others to Christ continually in Lebanon,
Tennessee, and throughout the whole world.
That is our mission that will get us continuously growing to
our vision.
Let's pray this morning.
Father, I thank you just once again for who you are.
Thank you, God, that you are here in the midst of us.
God, I pray that we never neglect or never ignore the
fact that the almighty God is with us right here
right now, God, we thank you.
I pray your Holy Spirit can roam freely in this place.
God, give me the words to speak, and those that have ears to hear,
may they hear, and it's in Jesus' name you pray, anybody said?
Amen.
Now you might be thinking, okay?
Because we've had this mission statement for about 9 years now, okay?
And there's still people.
I say, what's our mission?
They'll go, love, let live, love, love, love, right?
Listen, you might be thinking how in the world am I going to memorize
all these things.
As much as we would love for every person in our church
family to memorize these important statements, if you want to impress
your pastor, you go ahead and start trying, and next time you see me,
just spout it out, right?
Hey, pastor, here's our vision.
That would make me just feel really good.
But here's the thing.
Our priority must be to live them out.
Now, I do believe we need to know them to live them.
And, and, you know, I don't believe that we had to know all of scripture.
Memorize all the script.
I believe the Holy Spirit will remind us what we've been taught in scripture,
so we can be guided in the truth, but sometimes,
listen, when you get a culture of people that are all gathered
together in one name, that's Jesus, one purpose,
we just read, there's power in that.
There is effectiveness in that.
There is influence in that kind of unity.
And so our vision and mission means nothing if not clearly evidence by the way we live.
That's like someone quoting John 316 just because that's what they
learn as a kid, but they don't they're not living their life for Jesus.
That's like someone bashing someone in the head that, hey, Jesus said,
he's the way, the truth in the life, and no man comes to the Father except through him
without them living for Christ.
Listen, we better we better exemplify the
vision and mission before we start trying to tell everyone else about it.
We want to be living it out.
Now again, you might be thinking, well, that seems more difficult.
Maybe I'll just memorize it instead.
Well, here's the thing.
My question for you this morning is simple.
Who is Jesus to you?
There's a lot of false ideas circulating about who Jesus is.
As a matter of fact, this is a question that's been asked
for a long, long time, thousands of years.
Jesus asked the same question himself to the disciples.
Look at the text in Matthew 16, verses 13 through 14.
It's on the screen.
Now when Jesus came into the district of Caesarea, Philippi,
he was asking his disciples, who do people say that the Son of Man is?
In other words, who are people saying I am?
And they said, some say John the Baptist and
others Elijah, but still others, Jeremiah or one of
the prophets.
Notice there are many different opinions about who Jesus was,
even in the time of him walking this earth.
Church is no different today.
Some people believe that he is just a historical figure.
Others believe he is more mythical than real.
Some believe that Jesus was simply a good teacher.
There are those who believe that he was the 1st created being, then
you have those who believe that he was a prophet of God,
but he was not God.
Now, listen, this is a different the same answer the
disciples gave Jesus all the way back in this time.
Can I tell you something?
It matters who Jesus is.
It matters.
If every knee will bow and every tongue confess
that Jesus Christ is Lord, we better know who Jesus really is.
They say, John the Baptist, Elijah, Jeremiah, another great prophet.
But by the way, notice that these names they're attributing to Christ,
they're not bad names or bad people.
There's some powerhouses in scripture.
You understand what I'm saying?
You talking about Jeremiah, the weeping prophet, that dedicated entire
life to declaring God's word to a rebellious people,
Elijah, who did all the miracles that we see in scripture when
he was ministering, John the Baptist, who prepared the way of the Lord.
We're talking about some big time comparisons here, but
they're not Jesus.
That same John the Baptist says, I'm not I'm not worthy to baptize this man.
Hey, someone will come after me Christ, who is greater than I.
That's what John the Baptist said.
You know what Jesus said about John the Baptist?
There's no one born a woman greater than him.
In other words, what we're saying here is that we're talking about some big names.
We're talking about some big believers, some big missionaries
to this world, but they're not Christ, brothers and
sisters, we need to come to the realization that if we are wrong about Jesus,
we are wrong about everything, no matter how good it sounds.
There's a lot of teaching out there today.
That if you're not careful, you can listen to it and think, man, that
sounds real good, but if you just if you just listen through the unction
of the Holy Spirit, the Spirit will discern what is right and wrong.
There's a lot of false prophets.
There's a lot of wolves and sheep clothing that are trying to get the people
to believe in a Jesus that God's word does not say anything about.
So Jesus narrowed his question down from who everyone else says, Jesus
is, who his disciples believe he is.
By the way, can I tell you something?
It don't matter what everyone else says.
It matters what you believe.
You understand what I'm saying?
We need to believe correctly.
Matthew 16, verse 15 and 16, he said to them, but who do you say that I am?
Simon Peter answered, you are the Christ, the
son of the living God.
Can I tell you that it was this declaration that caused these men
to live and lose their life for the sake of Christ?
It was this declaration that most of them became martyrs for.
And I'm not talking about martyrs, just, you know, getting
in a line and getting shot in the head and being done.
Now, I'm talking about there were some that were crucified upside down.
There was some that was boiled.
I mean, you're talking about some horrendous ways of dying
for their faith.
Why?
Because they knew who Jesus was.
As Jews, they had an idea of who Jesus was supposed to be.
But when you meet the real Jesus, our ideas
and preconceived notions, fade and the Messiah
and risen savior takes over.
Truth will trump a lie every single time.
When Peter declared that Jesus was the Christ, he was saying that
Jesus was the Messiah, the promised one, the anointed
one, the one they had been waiting for, this term Christ
is used exclusively for Jesus of Nazareth in the New Testament.
There was no confusion here.
Now how did Jesus respond to that answer?
Because it was a great answer, amen?
Listen, Peter was a lot of things, but he would talk too much.
He would talk in the wrong time.
He was a hot head and a big mouth, but he answered correctly here.
You know what I'm saying?
So how did Jesus respond?
Well, if we keep it going in verses 17 through 19.
And Jesus said to him, blessed are you, Simon Barjona,
because flesh and blood did not reveal this to you, but my father who is in heaven.
I also say to you that you are Peter.
And upon this rock, I will build my church and the gates of Hades
will not overpower it.
I'll give you the keys of the kingdom of heaven, and whatever you bind on earth
shall have been bound in heaven, and whatever you loose on earth shall have
been loosed in heaven.
Now I want to share with you some clarifying truths here in the highly debated text we just read.
Who is the rock?
that Jesus built his church upon.
It's a big, that's a big question.
Is it Peter?
Is it faith?
Is it Jesus?
If all you get out of scripture, when
you study is what the English language says, you
will come into some very tough situations.
Because a lot, understand it, the Bible is not written in English originally.
Do we know this same man?
Okay, if you did not know that, that's okay.
We love you anyway, but the Bible is not written in English.
For example, that crazy pastor.
I don't know if you've seen it on social media that said that he can correct the Greek
with the KJV.
He is what we would call a moron.
Okay?
That's not real.
That doesn't make any sense at all, okay?
And so what I'm trying to say is, we gotta go deeper sometimes.
We got to make sure that we
just go off of what we think and what we know, what will happen is we'll
start putting in some, impose things in a text not there.
You say, why are you being so aggressive with this?
Well, the answer to this question, who is the
rock and who is the church built upon and what is the church built upon?
Is found in the terms that Jesus used.
The name Peter does indeed mean rock.
But the word for Peter means petros.
It is a masculine noun that means a detached stone,
a stone that might be thrown or easily moved.
In other words, this is a stone.
Think about it.
How easily Moo was Peter.
Now, I know Peter was a lot of good things, but there's 2 instances
that we know in scripture where he was easily moved.
He denied Christ 3 times, did he not?
Think about it.
The night that Jesus is crucified.
The one who you declared is the Messiah, the
anointed one, the promised one who came.
He denied him not once, not twice, but 3 times.
And not only that, the apostle Paul later on in
his ministry, had to correct him for
being too legalistic with the Jews and not opening up
the gospel to the Gentiles in the correct way.
In other words, listen, this Peter, Petros,
he was a rock that could be easily moved.
By the way, if you think that you're no better, be careful.
Listen, we can we can be going on on an awesome route.
We be thinking, man, nothing can move me.
I need you to understand something.
Take heed lest you fall.
If the great preacher and apostle Peter can fall, so can we.
So we see here that Petros, that's what that means.
That's the term used for Peter, this rock.
But the term Jesus used for rock right after that was
a different kind of rock.
The word for rock next mention is a different
Greek word, very similar, but it's Petra,
a feminine noun that means a mass of rock or a cliff.
It gives the idea of something foundational.
Petros is a rock that can be easily moved.
Petros is a rock, you're not moving it.
You're not getting it.
You understand what I'm saying?
So, so, okay, does this ring any bells here?
Well, Matthew 7, verse 24 through 25 says this.
Therefore, everyone who hears these words of mine and acts on them, maybe compare
it to a wise man who built his house on the rock.
Petros, a massive rock, a cliff, foundational.
And the rain fell and the floods came and the winds blew and slammed against that house.
And yet it did not fall for it had been founded on the rock.
So the word rock there, Petra means a
rock that is foundational.
Why is this important?
If you wait a minute, say I'm with you.
Jesus did not build his church upon Peter.
You with me?
He did not.
This is the tragic misunderstanding of the text.
The church is built upon the foundation of Jesus.
Scripture calls Jesus the chief cornerstone,
and we are built up by the proclamation that
Jesus, that chief cornerstone, is Lord, therefore we build up the house.
That is what the church is built upon.
Now you say, what does this have to do with our series?
Well, our vision and mission will never get accomplished if we do not have the correct foundation.
And when you have Jesus as your foundation, You
are inherently changed completely.
In other words, when Jesus is Lord, there is a
dramatic and eternal change in your life.
And part of that change is the values that
you live by.
And this is what we're basing this series on.
We are going to go one by one and look at what our core
values ought to be in order to build up his church.
You might be thinking, was that just the intro?
Yes, it was.
I want to say something about that, okay?
Everyone, you know, Thanksgiving's right around the corner, amen?
Yeah?
Are y'all excited about that?
Okay, I love me some Thanksgiving.
Y'all like Thanksgiving?
Amen.
Hey man, you know, you could have had me fooled just then.
I thought we had some ungrateful just pagans up in this place.
But listen, so it's going to be here before we know it, right?
I love eating Thanksgiving meal.
And I know, right?
Because I usually bring the cream corn and stuff, you know what I'm saying?
That's like my dish.
I do it all.
It's like 4 sticks of butter, a bunch of cheddar, you know, all the cheese and everything,
and it's just, it's amazing.
And so, but what happens, anyone, who cooks for Thanksgiving?
raise your hand.
Okay.
How long is the preparation for Thanksgiving meal?
Wednesday?
Thursday?
Do any of y'all start on Tuesday?
Okay, all right.
So you understand what I'm saying?
It takes a long time to prep that meal.
Amen?
Not only that, but if you have a mama like I've got,
you know, she puts all this decorations up and a
big old long table and everything's moved, and, you know, everyone's got a little name tag.
It's awkward when someone comes, we didn't know was there, and then she panics
and tries to find another name tag, and, you know, so it takes a long time.
Oh, that happens every single year, mama.
Anyway, but it takes a long time.
Now, you get to the table.
I get to my name, I grab my 3 plates,
and I go to the buffet line, amen?
You get back to the table.
How long does it take to eat?
About 5 minutes?
Maybe if you're one of those stage eaters.
Anyone's a stage eater, like you eat the corn 1st and the potatoes first.
That's just odd.
I just...
It don't take long.
Think about it.
You prepare 3 days for something that takes 20 minutes, if that.
And we're all cool with it, amen?
All right, then.
That was a long intro.
get over it
Sometimes it takes a long time to set the table, but once you get to eating,
it moves quickly.
So let's get to eating this morning, okay?
The reason why we were talking about this is this.
We're gonna look one by one at what our core values
ought to be in order to build up his church, especially
in a setting of Cedar Grove Baptist Church.
The title of this series is very simple.
It is upon this rock.
Upon this rock, we have seven core values here at Cedar Grove
that serve as the foundation to both our vision and mission.
We've already said that if we don't live out the mission and
live out the vision, then it doesn't matter.
These core values that we have together is what is going to
enable us to live it out.
And so the seven in order are as follows.
We have family, integrity, relationships,
commitment, unity, accountability, and excellence.
Now, next week, because we're working out
and hashing out some details, you're going to get a stewardship packet that
has our new yearly budget in there, has all the our
mission partners with some explanation of who they are and what and what they do.
And on the front of that, you're going to have these core values.
We want you to know and live out these values.
Okay?
But it's morning.
We're gonna go over the 1st one.
Here at Cedar Grove.
We will uphold the sanctity of family.
We're going to uphold the sanctity of family.
There are three primary ways that we are going to do this.
First, we uphold a sanctia family by making my
family a priority and intentionally spending
quality time with them.
We live in a world where schedules were our lives.
Someone say, amen.
I mean, it's this, it's that.
It's there's so much going on.
Work, sports, dance, other commitments or
what we center our entire life around.
Monday quickly turns to Friday.
And then the one day that we have off on Saturday, we spend doing more
work or running around, even than we did during the work week.
We have no time in our life, and I believe that's
the exact place that the enemy wants us.
He wants us to be in a rush.
He wants us to be busy.
Because in doing so, what has happened is we
have created isolation within the family.
Not only is the family isolated from other families,
but the family unit itself is isolated
within that family unit.
You say, what are you talking about?
Well, dad has his schedule.
Mom has her schedule.
Each kid has their own schedule.
Rarely do they intertwine outside of a stressful,
angry car rod to one of the appointments or practices.
We all have isolation.
This, in addition to the already established isolation,
it has become a cultural norm.
Well, if you're not keeping up, then you're behind.
If you're not signed up for every travel ball team,
then you're not going to make it.
I have news for you.
They probably not going to make it anyway.
You understand what I'm saying?
Some of y'all got hurt feelings just then.
You think your kid's going to the league.
You know what?
I hope they do.
Let them know, and they get that signing contract, I expect a check
to Cedar Girl Baptist Church for all the work we've done in them.
Amen.
But seriously, think about it.
And you say, well, you know, I don't really have any kids.
Okay?
Well, if you have a spouse, you need to be spending time with your spouse.
So often we give our goodbyes and I loves you when we leave the room.
The next time we actually talk to each other, we're laying in bed falling asleep.
You say, well, I don't even have a spouse.
Maybe you're here and you're single, you're living wholly dedicated to the Lord.
Listen, hey, then your church family is pretty important.
You got to stay together.
We gotta stay intentional.
And here's the scariest part of all this.
Why is this so important?
Well, we can never get our time back.
We can never get our time back.
This week.
Heather called me and husbands, if this
happens to you, you know, what I'm talking about.
She's like, well, Jake, I'm like, oh, oh, I don't like that tone.
Don't like that tone.
And, you know, I had just, I had
just talked to a brother in the Lord about just stressed
in life and trying to, you know, get where you need to be.
And it's just like, you know, budget and all things.
You know, just, just, you know, good accountability, brother talk,
you know, practical stuff, spiritual stuff.
And I'm like, you know, we went, literally, that day I went over the budget for the
month, and man, we were doing good.
Hey, it's like, you know what?
Hey, we got like, you know, a dollar.74 left.
And so, you know, we're I'm excited.
That's a good thing.
You know what I'm saying?
So we're like, we're ahead, baby.
And so we get through that, and a few hours
later, she calls and says, Jay, I'm like, what?
She said, a rock just popped up and hit my windshield.
And I didn't think it was cracked, but then I got back in the car after going inside.
And it's cracked all the way across the car.
What do I do?
I'm like, call somebody else.
I didn't say that.
I said, it's all good.
I didn't stress.
I started sweating.
You ever start sweating just instantly, just start seeing dollar signs.
And so, lo and behold, right?
You know, we sit here and and and we
go and and I call the insurance because I know
it's it's the year that it is and the kind of car
that it is, you know, it's not nothing is cheap anymore.
Understand what I'm saying?
It's not like, hey, yeah, just put some more glass on it.
No, no, no, no.
No, no.
This thing can go to the moon if it wants to, you know what I'm saying?
So it needs different kind of glass.
And so it has all these sensors and has all this stuff.
So I have to actually go through insurance, right?
And so anyway, had to pay deductible, whatever.
It is what it is.
But right after I literally just did our budget.
and thought we're doing good.
Has anyone been there?
Yeah?
So y'all like, man, I'm there right now, brother.
Help me, Lord.
But listen, hey, here's the thing, though.
You know why I didn't panic that much?
Because I can earn that money back somehow.
We can save a little bit each month.
We can do this, we can do that.
I can go.
I can mow the neighbor's yard, maybe, right?
There's things I can do.
I can go pick up a sub job, whatever it is.
Okay, I'm not worried about that, because I can earn it back.
You can't do that with time.
So there has been times to where I have set, I've laid
down in my bed at night, and I've thought, I've spent my entire day,
either complaining, griping,
yelling at the kids, irritated at Heather,
and now I'm landing a bed,
I will never get this day back.
That's scary.
That's heavy.
See, a financial issue, whatever, we can make that happen, right?
You know, we can do certain things, but with
time, you can never get it back.
Once spent, it has gone.
And the enemy has made us so busy and has deceived us
to think that this is how our lives should be, that we do not realize
that we are wasting much of it away.
Jesus spoke on investing our time properly in Matthew chapter
6, verse 19 through 21.
Do not store up for yourselves treasure, treasures on earth, where moth
and rust destroying, where thieves break in and steal, but store
up for yourselves treasures in heaven, where neither moth nor rust destroyers,
and where thieves do not break in or steal, for where your treasure
is, there your heart will be also.
What was the context and the background for what he was saying
here in Matthew 6.
It was anxiety.
It was worry.
Jesus was teaching not to be worried about the things of the world in
such a way that it controls your emotions and your spirit.
Now, this does not mean that you do not work.
This does not mean that sports and other extra things for your kids are a sin.
This does not mean that ambitious goals in life are bad.
What it means that if any of these things take away from your
devotion to Jesus and your family, they have
become a problem, you have set up an idol in your home.
By the way, we need parents to quit forcing their kids to fulfill their own personal,
unfulfilled dreams, and let kids be kids.
If there's one thing I have noticed, subbing for the last 9 years,
I've coached a little bit in my time.
It's that we say, well, they want to.
They don't know no different.
We forced them into a mindset to where if you if you're not as good as that
kid, if you don't make that team, if you don't do this, if you don't do good at
the at the recital, if you don't blah, blah, blah, you got to go there everywhere.
And we wonder why our kids will burn out by the time they're 12 years old.
You wonder why our kids are growing up so fast.
We're making them grow up so fast.
And not in a good way.
I'd rather my kid know all about Jesus than how to make a 3 pointer.
Now, listen, I want my kid to know how to make a three point or two.
You understand what I'm saying?
3rd or 4th down on the list.
All I'm trying to say is it's not bad, but it can very quickly become an idol.
We're teaching our children that if they are not busy from wake up to sundown, they aren't doing something right.
We are also teaching them that Jesus is only for when we have time for him.
So how do we balance this?
How do we break the mode of keeping up with all these worldly standards and pressures?
Because listen, I'm going to tell you right now.
Before I had kids, I said statements like this.
Anyone ever said something before they had kids?
And now you're like, that was dumb.
My kid will never sleep in my bed.
Okay.
You know, the storm last night.
I literally, I woke up.
I turned around because the door is right here and
I usually sleep to my backside to the door, right?
I just, I don't know, it's just comfortable for me.
And I knew that my daughters were about to be walking through that
door, and if I don't prepare for it, I'm going to get scared to death and probably
smack one of them because, you know, they're like, you know what I'm saying?
And so I just went ahead, woke up, and I turned because I was waiting for them
in the storm to walk in the door, jump in bed with us.
They don't used to do that, but, you know, it was kind of a scary storm.
I was a little scared myself.
And so they jumped in, really jumps in the bed, and then
I go, hey, I know your sister's gonna wake up upstairs and
freak out because you're not there.
Go ahead, go get her, tell her to jump in.
She runs down, it goes, like that right there.
Instantly, here it is.
And she's running right back to me, jumps my heart.
Listen, sometimes we say things that will never do.
And that's not what with my kids.
It's one of those things to where I've said before, before kids.
I'll ne my kid will never be so dedicated to a sport,
will never be do this, never do that outside.
Like that is, that is not even a temptation of mine.
It cannot happen.
Church is number one.
And listen, I still believe that.
But then you start seeing certain skills in your kids.
You understand what I'm saying?
They start showing, hey, I'm good at this, so I'm good at that.
Or they enjoy that.
And then, hey, you enjoy going out and doing these things.
Listen, you don't think the world does that on purpose.
We are tempted in every direction to put Jesus last.
We had to make the decision now that we are going to
put him 1st and then our family.
And so we see here, what is the balance?
What Jesus later says in that same chapter in verse 33 through 34,
Matthew 6, but seek 1st his kingdom and his righteousness,
and all these things will be added to you.
So do not worry about tomorrow.
For tomorrow we'll care for itself.
Each day has enough trouble of its own.
By the way, this is not promoting laziness.
This is promoting priority and intentionality.
If you're somebody who looks for a reason to
not serve, that's not what we're talking about here.
That's just lazy.
So what does the perfect day look like for your family?
Most of us, if we were honest, would describe a day void of spiritual things.
Oh, well, you know, perfect day for us is going to the lake and going
to eat and doing this, doing that.
Listen, hey, I get it.
But where's Jesus in any of that?
We say, whoa, well, he's in Korea.
I understand that.
But where's discipleship in that?
It's not bad, but where is your heart?
Where is your treasure?
So we are going to hold uphold the sanctity of our family, and
we're going to do so by making my family a priority and intention, and
intentionally spending quality time with them.
But that's not all.
We're moving quickly here.
To do this, we also do it by making the Bible the primary source of instruction.
There's a saying that people say when they learn something, you learn something new every day.
You ever said that like, man, oh, I didn't know that.
You learn something, you every day.
Well, that is more true than we know.
We all retain knowledge throughout the day that has some level of
influence on our actions.
But as believers, those who profess Jesus' Lord, we must
take heed to the instruction in scripture.
This is not a new truth.
When God gave the law to Moses, and Moses gave
the law to the people.
It was not just some superficial handing down of one liners.
It was not like how we parent today, like, don't do that.
I'm going to whoop you.
And then 24 times after, we say the same thing.
Don't do that.
I'm going to whoop you.
You're going to go to time out, do this.
That's not what this law was about.
You got to understand when he gave the law, it was to be obeyed.
It was the primary instruction on how they were
to live, their lives, and Moses made this clear in Deuteronomy
chapter 6, verse one through 7.
Now this is the commandment, the statutes and the judgments which the
Lord your God has commanded me to teach you, that you might
do them in a land where you were going over to possess it, so
that you and your son, and your grandson might fear the Lord
your God, to keep all his statutes and his commandments, which I command you all
the days of your life, and then your days may be prolonged.
Oh, Israel, you should listen and be careful to do it,
that it may dwell with you, that it may be well with
you, and that you may multiply greatly, just the Lord, the God of
your fathers has promised you in a land flowing with milk and honey.
Hear, O Israel, the Lord is our God, the Lord is one.
Ye shall love the Lord, your God with all your heart, and with all your soul,
and with all your might.
These words which I am commanding you today shall
be on your heart.
You shall teach them diligently to your sons and shall talk
of them when you sit in your house.
And when you walk by the way, and when you lie down, and when you
rise up.
In other words, he's not just giving this to put on a plaque
on the wall just for decoration, this is how they are to live their lives.
Church, if we are not founded on God's word, we will be given to
any and other worldly distractions that promise wisdom.
Why do we put so much investment and time into our children and youth programs?
Because as a church, we want to come alongside you in this mission to
biblically educate the next generation.
But if the 2 hours that your kid is
here at the church or your family is here at the church, if
that's all you get, if you go home, we cannot overcome a
whole week of just not living for Jesus.
The church is not, church can't do that.
It was never planned to be that way.
And so we are coming alongside you to help disciple
and to grow you in the faith.
But we cannot outdo what is and is not done at home.
Do we cherish God's word?
When we pick up the Bible, is it a burden or a blessing?
I can always base where I am with the Lord and how close I
am when I pick up God's word to read, do I get
excited or do I huff and puff?
You say preacher.
You huff and puff when you, no, no, no.
When I'm too busy.
And I've forgotten, and I'm sitting there and I'm watching TV,
and I'm thinking, man, I got to get up and go.
listen, I know something is wrong.
My priorities are not where they need to be.
Listen, I don't want, I don't, as much as I let the Duck Dynasty
Revival TV show right now, we love it.
Oh man, we love it.
I am not country, but if that's country, sign me up for country.
Amen?
That's some good country right there.
But listen, my kids love it.
If that's all the education they get, I'm doing something wrong.
They gotta know what God's word says about it.
Y'all women say amen.
So we're going to continue.
What do we base our daily decisions on?
What the world says or what God says, and that brings to the
3rd thing that we must do to uphold the sanctity of the family.
We do so by daily praying for my family, and with my family, not just for but with.
If there was a defining characteristic of the early believers, if the early
believers had a set of core values, prayer would be on the top of the list.
We see this in Acts 114.
These all with one mind were continually devoting themselves
to prayer.
What does it take for you to pray?
This is a question that could expose your mindset on the power of prayer.
Do we pray only in emergency?
Only in time of need, only when things are bad.
Paul told the believers in Thessalonica in one Thessalonians
517, pray without ceasing.
He was not telling them to be upon their knees all day
with their eyes closed and their heads bowed praying.
He was saying, with whatever you do, make sure you're praying.
Listen, you do realize, River, she blessed
the food before we watched the game yesterday.
And I was so blessed by it.
She prayed for everything but the food.
Hey, man, you know what I'm saying?
Like it was just the 25 minute prayer, no food mentioned.
But either way, she prayed, her eyes were wide stinking open.
She was looking at buddy while she's praying.
Now listen, we think here and say, well, that's not,
God didn't get to heaven.
Listen, hey, you know what she was doing?
She was looking at who was joining her in prayer.
you know when I was down?
I was just looking right at her, just proud that she understands the power of prayer.
We got to understand something.
We can pray with our eyes open.
We can pray in a posture of humility physically,
but as long as our heart is humbled before the Lord, we can pray
without ceasing.
The fight, the battle, the need for closeness with God never ends.
Therefore our communication with him should not end.
Again, if you're married and think about it, when you were if
you were dating before you were married, the communication was crazy, was it not?
I'm talking about you couldn't do nothing without having to check in, right?
I remember for the 1st when me and Heather 1st got married,
I could not go to a restaurant that she liked and she was not there.
I literally, I had to tell my buddies, hey, where are we going?
They say sake.
I'd be like, okay, well, and then I tell Heather, Heather be like, uh, you know I like sake.
Why you going to socky?
I'm like, Heather, that's kind of crazy.
And she goes, no, I want to go to Sake with you.
So, and then she'd do that.
It's special when we go together.
We can go to date night.
So you know what I do?
Hey guys, we can't go to soccer because my wife likes soccer and she's not with us right now.
Look, communication was crazy in that time, right?
You want to know where each other were.
We want to know this.
You want to know that?
You were doing check-ins all the time.
Oh, baby, I love you.
blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
Well, guess what?
A few years goes behind marriage.
Guess what stops?
All that.
Where are you going to eat?
Uh, uh, Staki.
Oh, cool.
How long you gonna be?
I don't know.
Good.
You see what I'm saying?
Things change.
If you're not careful, if you're not intentional, things will change,
but you know what a marriage needs, a marriage needs constant communication.
Because guess what?
You know what I know?
I know the enemy's attacking me.
And I know the enemy's attacking her.
Therefore, I know that we need to communicate because we're fighting this battle together.
We've sang part of the song.
I think it was the first one.
Maybe call to worship, that the battle was not over.
Listen, the battle is won, but it is not over.
We were on the winning side, but there's still fight to do.
God still has us here for a reason.
We are to pray without ceasing.
If this is true for your life personally, it's also for your family.
If there's no communication with God, if there's no communication with
your family, the enemy will have a foothold there.
There is power and prayer.
There is power in praying together.
If there's any lesson that we can hand down to the next generation,
is that prayer works.
First John 5, 14.
And this is the confidence that we have in him, that if we ask anything according to
his will, he heareth us.
If your kids think you doubt prayer, they're definitely going to doubt prayer.
If you pray only when things are bad.
Guess when?
They're gonna pray.
Only when things are bad.
If you only pray with your family because that's just, you know, okay,
hey, everyone buy your God, thankful for your name, man.
Listen, I do these things.
We gotta be careful.
Our families, we need to pray together.
See to grow up, we're going to be a church of God, church that God desires us to be.
If we're going to live out this mission, we cannot have
a holy church without holy families.
This is the 1st value that we have set as part of the foundation of our gathering.
So let me ask you, what about your family?
It's quality time a priority.
Is the Bible the primary instruction in your home?
Where does prayer have its place in your daily schedule and routine?
I don't speak, I'm speaking to myself here today.
This is not a drill.
The enemy is after our families, and we must fight together.
So it has bound eyes closed all this place.